Finding Aid for Charles B. Haydon Papers, 1852-1864
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Charles B. Haydon Papers 1852-1864 1861-1864
Haydon, Charles B., 1834-1864.
1 linear ft. and 1 microfilm reel
Student at the University of Michigan (1854-1857) from Kalamazoo, Michigan, who served in the Second Michigan Infantry during the Civil War. Civil War diaries describing his army career; also University of Michigan student notebooks, ca. 1854, including one on a history course by James R. Boise; a sketch book and personal account book; letter to his brother Arthur (1855?) relating to his student experiences; and photograph.
851446 Aa 2, mf99c
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The diaries were donated in 1949 or 1950 by Ione Haydon (donor no. 2710 ), Charles Haydon's niece, and came to the library through Arba Moulton (donor no. 3929 ), former editor and publisher of the Decatur Republican, which had published transcriptions of the diary entries in the 1940s.
The collection is open for research.
The originals of the Haydon Civil War diaries are also available at the Bentley Histoircal Library, but access is limited to the microfilm copy.
Charles B. Haydon was born in 1834 in Kalamazoo, Michigan. He attended college at the University of Michigan during the years 1854-1857, but did not graduate.
He practices law in Kalamazoo until he joined the army in response to President Lincoln's call for volunteers to fight in the Civil War. From 1861 to 184, Haydon served in Company E of the Second Michigan Infantry, starting as a private and rising to the rank of Lieutenant Colonel. During his service in the army, Haydon kept a diary in pocket-size notebooks. His unit was involved in numerous significant battles: Bull Run, Second Bull Run, Fredericksburg, Vicksburg, and Jackson. Haydon was wounded badly in the latter battle in July 1863.
On March 14, 1864, Haydon died of pneumonia in Cincinnati, Ohio, while his regiment was on the way home to Michigan for a rest.
The Haydon collection consist of student notebooks (ca. 1852-1859) while a student at the University of Michigan, diaries from his service in the Civil War (1861-1864), a family letter, and a portrait of Haydon in his military uniform.
The diaries of Charles Haydon are available in For country, cause & leader: the Civil War journal of Charles B. Haydon edited by Stephen W. Sears ( New York: Ticknor & Fields, 1993)
Subjects:
Boise, James Robinson, 1815-1895.; Haydon, Arthur W., 1844-1918.; Haydon, Charles B., 1834-1864.; Kalamazoo (Mich.); Law.; Soldiers--Michigan--Kalamazoo.; United States. Army. Michigan Infantry Regiment, 2nd (1861-1865). Company E.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Classical Studies.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1851-1860.; University of Michigan--Student notebooks.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Haydon, Charles B., 1834-1864.; Soldiers--Michigan--Kalamazoo.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.
Genre/Form:
Diaries.; Photographs.
- University of Michigan
  - Student notebook; alphabetical listing of world history, arranged chronologically under each letter, undated (Box 1)
  - Student notebook, 1852-1854 (Box 1)
  - Student notebook, 1854-1857 (Box 1)
  - Student notebook, 1859 (Box 1)
  - Letter to his brother Arthur, 1855? (Box 1)
- Civil War service
  - Diaries
    (pocket-size except where indicated)
    - April 30-June 9, 1861 (Reel 1)
    - June 11-July 26, 1861 (Reel 1)
    - July 27-August 16, 1861 (Reel 1)
    - August 17-August 31, 1861 (Reel 1)
    - September 1-September 19, 1861 (Reel 1)
    - September 20-October 3, 1861 (Reel 1)
    - October 4-October 17, 1861 (Reel 1)
    - October 17-November 28, 1861 (Reel 1)
    - November 30-December 29, 1861 (Reel 1)
    - December 30, 1861-January 14, 1862 (Reel 1)
    - February 16-April 3, 1862 (Reel 1)
    - April 3-May 18, 1862 (Reel 1)
    - December 6, 1863-February 21, 1864 (Reel 1)
    - May 19, 1862-February 8, 1864 (Reel 1)
      (transcription copies made by Haydon of smaller diaries and later bound into a volume; included are two pocket-size diaries, July-August 1862)
    - Typed transcripts of diaries compiled by Ida C. Brown, April 30, 1861-January 24, 1863 (Reel 1)
    - Handwritten transcripts by Ida C. Brown, July 18-December 21, 1861 (Reel 1)
  - Other materials
    - Miscellaneous clippings and biographical information (Reel 1)
    - Portrait of Charles Haydon in military uniform
      (not microfilmed; in vault)
Related Material
Grand Valley State University Libraries holds the following map, part of its Lemmen Collection on Lincoln and the American Civil War:
Lloyd's official map of the state of Virginia: from actual surveys by order of the executive 1828 & 1859 / corrected and revised by J.T. Lloyd to 1862, from surveys made by Capt. W. Angelo Powell, of the U. S. Topographical Engineers of Gen. Rosencrans' staff. Publisher: New York: J.T. Lloyd, [1862].
On the inside front cover is written in brown ink: "Charles B. Haydon / 1st Lt. Co. I & Actg. Adjt. / 2nd Mich. Inf. / Rifle Pits in front of Richmond Va. / June 21st, 1862"
Call Number: G3880 1862 .L55